Inventory of the Abercrombie & Fitch Quarterly Catalog Collection, 1997-2007
The John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Abercrombie & Fitch Quarterly Catalog Collection, 1997-2007
Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library, Duke University
Abercrombie & Fitch Co.
3.0 Linear Feet 34 Items
Abercrombie and Fitch was founded in 1892 as a sporting goods supplier and expedition outfitter. It currently specializes in upscale sportswear aimed at children and young adults.
The Abercrombie & Fitch Quarterly Catalog Collection consists of a run of lifestyle-oriented clothing catalogs issued between 1997 and 2007. The catalog featured articles on a wide range of youth popular culture and lifestyle topics, along with numerous photographs by Bruce Weber. Articles included advice, music and movie reviews, and profiles and interviews with celebrities and cultural critics such as philosopher Slavoj Žižek. The Creative Director for the catalog series was Sam Shahid, who had previously worked in the in-house advertising agencies for Calvin Klein and Banana Republic. After 2003, the lifestyle content and controversial photography was scaled back to focus more narrowly on seasonal fashion.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, collection may contain materials to which the Acknowledgment of Legal Responsibilities and Privacy Rights form applies. Patrons must sign this form before using this collection.
Also, all or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. Consequently, there may be a 24-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Abercrombie & Fitch Quarterly Catalog Collection were received by the Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library as a gift from John Taormina in 2008.
Historical Note
Abercrombie & Fitch Historical Timeline
Chronology List
1892 David T. Abercrombie founded a sporting goods store in his name in New York, N.Y.
1900 Ezra H. Fitch became partner in the David T. Abercrombie Co.
1904 Store incorporated as Abercrombie & Fitch
1907 Abercrombie resigned; Fitch took over management of the store but kept the name
1909 First mail-order catalogs distributed, in a run of 50,000
1910 Sportswear for women introduced
1928 Fitch retired; James S. Cobb named as President
Circa 1929 Sporting goods company Von Langerke & Detmold (known in Chicago as Von Langerke & Antoine) purchased
1930 Griffin & Howe, a New York gun shop, purchased
1961 John H. Ewing named as President
1968 First warehouse sale conducted
1970 William Humphries named as President
1976 Chapter 11 bankruptcy filed
1977 Abercrombie & Fitch stores closed
1978 Abercrombie & Fitch name bought by Oshman's Sporting Goods
1979 Beverly Hills store opened, specializing in sportswear and fitness equipment
1988 25 of 27 stores purchased by The Limited, Inc.; focus on apparel
1992 Marketing shifted focus toward upscale youth
1997 Abercrombie & Fitch Quarterly catalog debut
1998 Abercrombie & Fitch spun off as an independent entity
2003 Abercrombie & Fitch Quarterly catalog ceased publication
Upon the demise of the Quarterly in 2003, Abercrombie & Fitch continued to issue seasonal catalogs, but the lifestyle content was largely replaced by fashion photography.
Collection Overview
The Abercrombie & Fitch Quarterly Catalog Collection consists of a run of lifestyle-oriented clothing catalogs issued between 1997 and 2007. The catalog featured articles on a wide range of youth popular culture and lifestyle topics, along with numerous photographs by Bruce Weber. Articles included advice, music and movie reviews, and profiles and interviews with celebrities and cultural critics such as philosopher Slavoj Žižek. The Creative Director for the catalog series was Sam Shahid, who had previously worked in the in-house advertising agencies for Calvin Klein and Banana Republic. After 2003, the lifestyle content and controversial photography was scaled back to focus more narrowly on seasonal fashion.
The collection is arranged chronologically by issue
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Weber, Bruce, 1946-
Žižek, Slavoj--Interviews.
Abercrombie & Fitch.
Commercial catalogs.
Mail-order business.
Advertising, Direct-mail--United States.
Advertising and youth--United States--History--20th century.
Advertising and youth--United States--History--21st century.
Advertising and youth--United States.
Advertising--Brand name products.
Advertising--Clothing and dress.
Direct marketing.
Fashion photography.
Fashion--Social aspects--United States--20th century.
Fashion--Social aspects--United States--21st century.
Popular culture--United States.
Popular culture--United States--20th century.
Popular culture--United States--21st century.
Target marketing--United States.
United States--Social life and customs--20th century.
United States--Social life and customs--21st century.
Mail order catalogs.
Trade catalogs.
John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Related Material
Additional examples of catalogs and other direct-mail materials may be found in the Sears, Roebuck and Company Catalog Collection; several collections within the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives--the Detroit Office Records, Account File Collection, Ford Collateral Literature, and the Bertram Metter Papers. Materials relating to fashion and apparel advertising may be found in the J. Walter Thompson Company Domestic Advertisements Collection (Benetton, New York Dress Institute); the Bates Worldwide, Inc. Records (Foot Locker, Pacific Sunwear); and the Wells, Rich, Greene, Inc. Records (Warnaco/Warner's). Individually cataloged items may be located by searching the Duke University Libraries online catalog.
Detailed Description of Collection
- Quarterly Catalogs, 1997-2007, 10 Boxes
  - 1997, Fall (Premier Issue) (Box 1)
  - 1997, Christmas
  - 1998, Spring Break
  - 1998, Summer
  - 1998, Back to School
  - 1998, Christmas (Box 2)
  - 1999, Spring Break
  - 1999, Summer
  - 1999, Back to School (Box 3)
  - 1999, Christmas
  - 2000, Spring Break
  - 2000, Summer (Box 4)
  - 2000, Back to School
  - 2000, Christmas
  - 2001, Spring Break (Box 5)
  - 2001, Summer
  - 2001, Back to School
  - 2001, Christmas (Box 6)
  - 2002, Spring Break
  - 2002, Summer
  - 2002, Back to School (Box 7)
  - 2002, Christmas
  - 2003, Spring Break
  - 2003, Summer (Box 8)
  - 2003, Back to School
  - 2003, Christmas
  - 2004, Spring Break (Box 9)
  - 2004, Christmas
  - 2004, Christmas (alternate cover)
  - 2005, Spring Break
  - 2005, Back to School
  - 2005, Christmas
  - 2006, Spring Break (Box 10)
  - 2006, Summer
  - 2006, Back to School
  - 2006, Christmas
  - 2007, Spring Break